Bingham Associates Fund Records MS228
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Bingham Associates Fund Records
1932 -- 1985
1900 -- 1990
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Tufts Medical Center
Bingham Associates Fund
Tufts-New England Medical Center
MS228
7.2 Linear Feet
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 4 series: Subject files; Publications; Minutes; and Legacy collection documentation.
Custodial History
This collection was originally part of the archives of the New England Medical Center (NEMC), which closed in 1990. The collection was processed by Dave Nathan, archivist at the NEMC archives, in July 1989, and had the following NEMC acquisition number: 85-38.
In spring 2013, NEMC material was transferred from NEMC to a restoration company for conservation treatment, and was then transferred to off-site storage in custody of Digital Collections and Archives (DCA). In December 2014 and January 2015, the material was transferred to DCA for processing. Some material originally in the NEMC archives was not transferred to DCA, due to either poor condition or loss.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains publications, meeting minutes, and administrative files of the Bingham Associates Fund, as well as the Bingham Advisory Committee. Physician files, annual reports, and correspondence, as well as information about regional medical programs, are also included. The physical collection documentation folder of this collection includes copies of Dave Nathan's original finding aid entries as well as copies of the original acquisition records.
This collection suffered extensive water damage due to a flood before it was in the custody of DCA. It underwent conservation efforts before processing, but several materials, particularly folders, scrapbooks, and bound volumes, are still warped or retain a musty odor. In addition, many items are fragile, and must be handled carefully.
Biographical / Historical
The Bingham Associates Fund (BAF), sometimes known as the Bingham Associates Program, was one of the earliest regional medical programs in the nation. It was founded in 1932 by the financial backing of William Bingham II (1879-1955), a patient of Dr. Joseph Pratt. It was established to assist in the development of rural health care in the state of Maine. Medical staff from the New England Medical Center and students from the Tufts College School of Medicine were sent to Maine, courtesy of this program.
The mission of the BAF was to provide medical care to the people of Maine by providing them access to physicians normally working in Boston, nearly 200 miles south. After several conversations between William Bingham and Dr. George Farnsworth, Bingham agreed to finance the project. It was established as a non-profit organization with Dr. Pratt, Farnsworth, and Dr. John Gehring comprising the first Board of Trustees. The Fund provided Dr. Pratt with a grant of $1000 to send physicians to Rumford, Maine to give monthly clinics on medical techniques to local doctors. It went on to build laboratories and provide pathologists to hospitals throughout the state.
The Bingham Fund also sponsored the diagnostic ward at the Boston Dispensary, as well as a joint program with the Tufts College School of Medicine. The BAF was thus centered around Tufts University and the newly established New England Medical Center.
After the alliance of New England Center Hospitals, Inc. and the Tufts University School of Medicine, officially incorporated as Tufts-New England Medical Center in 1965, BAF assets were absorbed into the corporation. In 1974 the BAF dissolved, with an understanding that their funds be retained in the Bingham Fund Endowment. Residents from Maine comprised the Bingham Advisory Council, which dictated the use of the endowment income to the T-NEMC Board.
Bingham, William, 1879-1955; Bingham Associates Fund; New England Medical Center; Tufts-New England Medical Center; Tufts College. Medical School; Tufts University. School of Medicine; Hospitals--Medical staff; Primary medical care; Charity organization; Maine; Bingham Associates Program; Gould Academy; Boston Dispensary; University history; Medical care; Medicine -- History; Medical history
- Subject files, 1900 -- 1985; MS228.001; 3.6 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains histories, reports, news clippings, annual reports, files on individual doctors and staff members, articles from medical journals, information on the Gould Academy in Maine, and publications.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Report on feasibility of a regional medical center in Central Aroostook county, 1966; MS228.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - The History of Gould Academy, 1953; MS228.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - Samuel Proger, 1965 -- 1979; MS228.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Curran Tapes, 1940 -- 1970; MS228.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - Emelie Burn, MS228.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - H. E. MacMahon M.D., 1970; MS228.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Roy Crosby M.D., 1949; MS228.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - Sidney Davidson, 1976 -- 1977; MS228.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
  - Alice Ettinger, 1970; MS228.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Dr. Gehring, 1929; MS228.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - Frederick H. Gerrish M.D., 1973; MS228.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - George T. Nilson, 1961 -- 1962; MS228.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Hospital Extension, 1965 -- 1966; MS228.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Maine Medical School, 1966; MS228.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - Hospital Extension, 1939; MS228.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - Gould Academy, MS228.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
  - Boston Medical Reports, 1966 -- 1967; MS228.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - WBII Trust for Charity, MS228.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
  - WBII Philanthropies, MS228.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
  - Joseph H. Pratt, 1942 -- 1945; MS228.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
  - BAF Chronology, 1900 -- 1962; MS228.001.001.00021 (Box 1)
  - Curran, 1960 -- 1976; MS228.001.001.00022 (Box 1)
  - Richard T. Chamberlain M.D., MS228.001.001.00023 (Box 1)
  - Bills to Dick Chamberlain, Rural Health Care, 1980; MS228.001.001.00024 (Box 1)
  - Notes from Exp. In Med. And correspondence, MS228.001.001.00025 (Box 1)
  - Medical Education, 1956 -- 1980; MS228.001.001.00026 (Box 1)
  - TUSM, 1951 -- 1953; MS228.001.001.00027 (Box 1)
  - 1941-1942, MS228.001.001.00028 (Box 1)
  - 1953, MS228.001.001.00029 (Box 1)
  - 1955, MS228.001.001.00030 (Box 1)
  - BAF booklet, Trustee-members hospital, 1959; MS228.001.001.00031 (Box 1)
  - 1961, MS228.001.001.00032 (Box 1)
  - 1967, MS228.001.001.00033 (Box 1)
  - Kelloge quote, 1962; MS228.001.001.00034 (Box 1)
  - AHEC, 1972 -- 1977; MS228.001.001.00035 (Box 1)
  - Brooks Ryder, 1976; MS228.001.001.00036 (Box 1)
  - Guest Resident Program, 1939; MS228.001.001.00037 (Box 1)
  - Hill-Burton, 1969; MS228.001.001.00038 (Box 1)
  - General Source, 1958; MS228.001.001.00039 (Box 1)
  - Proger, 1942; MS228.001.001.00040 (Box 1)
  - Farnsworth Building, 1949; MS228.001.001.00041 (Box 1)
  - Diagnostic clinics, 1978 -- 1979; MS228.001.001.00042 (Box 1)
  - William M. Throop Jr., 1920 -- 1953; MS228.001.001.00043 (Box 1)
  - BAF Bibliography, 1932 -- 1944; MS228.001.001.00044 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1980, MS228.001.001.00045 (Box 1)
  - BAF Compo, 1932 -- 1964; MS228.001.001.00046 (Box 1)
  - Bulletin NECH (later with TUSM), 1950 -- 1953; MS228.001.001.00047 (Box 1)
  - Curran, Dr. Jean BAF, 1971 -- 1978; MS228.001.001.00048 (Box 1)
  - Trustee Lists BAF, 1963 -- 1964; MS228.001.001.00049 (Box 1)
  - BAF Van Buren Community Hospital, 1975 -- 1977; MS228.001.001.00050 (Box 1)
  - BAF Consultants Cons. Emeritus, 1975 -- 1976; MS228.001.001.00051 (Box 1)
  - Bingham Historical Materials, 1950 -- 1970; MS228.001.001.00052 (Box 1)
  - George Robertson, 1977; MS228.001.001.00053 (Box 1)
  - A Survey of Nursing Needs in Arrostook County, Maine, 1960; MS228.001.001.00054 (Box 1)
  - North Carolina Medical Care Commission, National Committee for the Medical School Survey Final Report, 1946; MS228.001.001.00055 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1949 -- 1978; MS228.001.001.00056 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1934 -- 1976; MS228.001.001.00057 (Box 1)
  - Al Waitkus, MS228.001.001.00058 (Box 1)
  - BAF/NEMC pharmacy program, 1974 -- 1975; MS228.001.001.00059 (Box 1)
  - Sanger report, 1946; MS228.001.001.00060 (Box 1)
  - BAF program descriptions, 1968 -- 1979; MS228.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - Jean A. Curran, M.D., papers, 1943 -- 1962; MS228.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Center Arrostook Hospital Medical Center, 1965 -- 1966; MS228.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Lee Bern Manuscripts from Dr. Curran tapes 1-6, 1957 -- 1959; MS228.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Journal of the Maine Medical Association, 1966; MS228.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - Boston Medical Reports, Annual Reports, 1965; MS228.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Continuing Education, BMR - GRP, 1966 -- 1967; MS228.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - BMR, 1965 -- 1981; MS228.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - Boston Medical Reports Grants No. 21-3 A-64, 1965; MS228.001.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - Boston Medical Reports catalog of available films and videotapes, 1966; MS228.001.002.00010 (Box 2)
  - Osteopathy, 1978; MS228.001.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - Boston Today Futures, 1979; MS228.001.002.00012 (Box 2)
  - William Bingham II, 1955; MS228.001.002.00013 (Box 2)
  - RMP & BAF, 1967 -- 1969; MS228.001.002.00014 (Box 2)
  - RMP/Tri-State, 1968 -- 1971; MS228.001.002.00015 (Box 2)
  - RMP, 1967 -- 1969; MS228.001.002.00016 (Box 2)
  - Rural Medicine, 1977; MS228.001.002.00017 (Box 2)
  - Social Service, MS228.001.002.00018 (Box 2)
  - Tufts University School of Medicine, 1929 -- 1971; MS228.001.002.00019 (Box 2)
  - T-NEMC - lot, 1976; MS228.001.002.00020 (Box 2)
  - Ziskind Dedication, 1959; MS228.001.002.00021 (Box 2)
  - Bingham Program, 1968 -- 1973; MS228.001.002.00022 (Box 2)
  - Kurt Neumann, BAF Overview, 1960; MS228.001.002.00023 (Box 2)
  - NEMCH Today, 1979; MS228.001.002.00024 (Box 2)
  - Nursing, 1964; MS228.001.002.00025 (Box 2)
  - Medical Career Guidance, 1961 -- 1964; MS228.001.002.00026 (Box 2)
  - PG Program, 1937 -- 1953; MS228.001.002.00027 (Box 2)
  - Pratt Clinic, 1939 -- 1947; MS228.001.002.00028 (Box 2)
  - Regionalization, 1944 -- 1951; MS228.001.002.00029 (Box 2)
  - Radiology, MS228.001.002.00030 (Box 2)
  - Nursing, 1953 -- 1973; MS228.001.002.00031 (Box 2)
  - G.P. Training Program, 1949 -- 1956; MS228.001.002.00032 (Box 2)
  - H.E. MacMahon, 1963; MS228.001.002.00033 (Box 2)
  - Seminars in Medicine As a Career, 1964; MS228.001.002.00034 (Box 2)
  - Building Proger, facts, 1947 -- 1958; MS228.001.002.00035 (Box 2)
  - Primary Care Education - What is Feasible?, 1974; MS228.001.002.00036; Proger, Samuel; Robertson, George J.; Williams, Greer (Box 2)
  - Jean Curran, 1977; MS228.001.002.00037 (Box 2)
  - T-NEMC/BAF, 1963; MS228.001.002.00038 (Box 2)
  - Study of Student Interest in a Career as a New Health Care Specialist, 1974; MS228.001.002.00039; Daniel Yankelovich, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Unmet Needs in Medical Care of Rural People State of Maine, 1956; MS228.001.002.00040; Smillie, Wilson G.; Curran, Jean A. (Box 2)
  - Northern Oxford Health and Service Council, Inc. Financial Report, 1982; MS228.001.002.00041 (Box 2)
  - Bingham Program annual report, 1984 -- 1985; MS228.001.006.00001 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - BAF memorandum on review of accounting procedures, 1947; MS228.001.006.00002 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Born, Emilie, 1974 -- 1976; MS228.001.006.00003 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Advisory Committee annual meeting, 1976 -- 1977; MS228.001.006.00004 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Staff meeting program administration, 1976 -- 1977; MS228.001.006.00005 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Advisory Committee annual meeting, 1975 -- 1976; MS228.001.006.00006 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Staff meeting program administration, 1974 -- 1975; MS228.001.006.00007 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Annual staff meeting, 1978; MS228.001.006.00008 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Chamberlain, Richard, 1977; MS228.001.006.00009 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Advisory Committee annual meeting, 1977 -- 1978; MS228.001.006.00010 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Advisory Committee annual meeting, 1979 -- 1980; MS228.001.006.00011 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Literature about BAF, 1962 -- 1977; MS228.001.006.00012 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Bingham annual meeting, 1979; MS228.001.006.00013 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Proposed budget, 1976 -- 1978; MS228.001.006.00014 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Advisory Committee annual meeting, 1978 -- 1979; MS228.001.006.00015 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Annual staff meeting, 1984; MS228.001.006.00016 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Advisory Council meeting, 1972; MS228.001.006.00017 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Continuing education grant, 1965 -- 1966; MS228.001.006.00018 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Area Health Survey, Knox County, Maine, 1963-10; MS228.001.006.00019; Viguers, Richard T. (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Medical Television in Massachusetts: A Five to Ten Year Projection, 1967; MS228.001.006.00020 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Publications, 1945 -- 1979; MS228.001.006.00021 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Bingham Associates Program broad objectives draft, 1951; MS228.001.006.00022 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
  - Bingham Associates Fund of Massachusetts, 1946 -- 1950; MS228.003.006.00023 (Box MS228 Shared 1)
- Publications, 1932 -- 1973; MS228.002; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains conference proceedings, reports, annual reports, and bulletins.
  - Area Health Survey for the Memorial Hospital, North Conway, NH, 1964-06; MS228.002.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - Report to Henrietta Goodall Hospital, 1962-01; MS228.002.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Report to Emerson Hospital, 1960-10; MS228.002.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - Survey of Nursing Needs in Aroostook County, Maine, 1960; MS228.002.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - Medical Care in the State of Maine, 1956 -- 1962; MS228.002.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - New England Medical Center Bulletin (1 of 2), 1947 -- 1951; MS228.002.003.00006 (Box 3)
    Non-consecutive.
  - New England Medical Center Bulletin (2 of 2), 1951 -- 1959; MS228.002.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - Bingham Associates Program News (1 of 2), 1948 -- 1953; MS228.002.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Bingham Associates Program News (2 of 2), 1953 -- 1959; MS228.002.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - Bingham Associates Consultation Services, 1952; MS228.002.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - Bingham Associates Program Training School for Junior Laboratory Technicians, 1957; MS228.002.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - Annual Report, appendix II, III, VI, 1951 -- 1952; MS228.002.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - Manual for Operating Room Technology, 1966; MS228.002.003.00013; Ginsberg, Frances; Brunner, Lillian S.; Cantlin, Vernita L.; Hurwitz, Alfred (Box 3)
  - Food Service Sanitation, 1973; MS228.002.003.00014; Litsky, Bertha Y. (Box 3)
  - Medical Care Use in Sweden and the United States, 1970; MS228.002.003.00015; Andersen, Ronald; Smedby, Bjorn; Anderson, Odin (Box 3)
  - Schedule of Activities for the Third Annual Student Seminar on Medicine as a Career, 1963; MS228.002.003.00016 (Box 3)
  - Annual report, 1932 -- 1939; MS228.002.003.00017 (Box 3)
  - Annual report, 1940; MS228.002.003.00018 (Box 3)
  - Annual report, 1941; MS228.002.003.00019 (Box 3)
  - Annual report, 1942; MS228.002.003.00020 (Box 3)
  - Annual report of the Medical Director, 1943; MS228.002.003.00021 (Box 3)
  - Annual report, 1944 -- 1947; MS228.002.003.00022 (Box 3)
  - Annual report, 1947; MS228.002.004.00001 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Annual report, 1949 -- 1952; MS228.002.004.00002 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Annual report, 1952 -- 1953; MS228.002.004.00003 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Annual report, 1953 -- 1954; MS228.002.004.00004 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Annual report, 1954 -- 1955; MS228.002.004.00005 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Annual report, 1955 -- 1956; MS228.002.004.00006 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Annual report, 1956 -- 1957; MS228.002.004.00007 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Annual report, 1957 -- 1959; MS228.002.004.00008 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Annual report, 1958 -- 1959; MS228.002.004.00009 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Annual report, 1965 -- 1966; MS228.002.004.00010 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Proceedings of Board of Trustees and Maine Advisory Council, 1963 -- 1971; MS228.002.004.00011 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Bingham-Kellogg-Boston University Regional Nursing Education Program annual report, 1951 -- 1952; MS228.002.004.00012 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Bingham-Kellogg-Boston University Regional Nursing Education Program annual report, 1952 -- 1953; MS228.002.004.00013 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Auditor's report, 1956; MS228.002.004.00014 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
- Minutes, 1967 -- 1990; MS228.003; 2.4 Linear Feet
  This series contains meeting minutes of the Bingham Associates Fund Advisory Council.
  - Advisory Council, general, 1971 -- 1972; MS228.003.004.00015 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Annual trustees meeting, 1972; MS228.003.004.00016 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Annual trustees meeting, 1972; MS228.003.004.00017 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Advisory Council annual meeting, 1973 -- 1974; MS228.003.004.00018 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Trustees annual meeting minutes, 1973 -- 1974; MS228.003.004.00019 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Advisory Committee meeting, 1980; MS228.003.004.00020 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Working folder, 1981; MS228.003.004.00021 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Advisory Committee meeting, 1981; MS228.003.004.00022 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Advisory Committee meeting, 1982; MS228.003.004.00023 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Bingham Program annual meeting, 1983; MS228.003.004.00024 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Annual meeting RTC copy and notes, 1983; MS228.003.004.00025 (Box MS228 Shared 2)
  - Advisory committee meeting, 1985; MS228.003.005.00001 (Box MS228 Shared 3)
  - Advisory committee meeting, 1982; MS228.003.005.00002 (Box MS228 Shared 3)
  - Advisory committee meeting extras, 1982; MS228.003.005.00003 (Box MS228 Shared 3)
  - Advisory committee annual meeting, 1983 -- 1984; MS228.003.005.00004 (Box MS228 Shared 3)
  - Staff meetings, 1983 -- 1984; MS228.003.005.00005 (Box MS228 Shared 3)
  - Kiwanis Pediatric Trauma Institute, 1980 -- 1990; MS228.003.005.00006 (Box MS228 Shared 3)
  - Bingham: annual meeting, 1983; MS228.003.005.00007 (Box MS228 Shared 3)
  - Report on regional medical programs to the president and the congress, 1967; MS228.003.005.00008 (Box MS228 Shared 3)
  - Proceedings: conference on regional medical programs, 1967; MS228.003.005.00009 (Box MS228 Shared 3)
  - Proceedings: conference workshops on regional medical programs, 1968; MS228.003.005.00010 (Box MS228 Shared 3)
- Legacy collection documentation, 1990; MS228.004; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains finding aids by NEMC archivist Dave Nathan, as well as NEMC acquisition records.
  - Legacy collection documentation folder, 1990; MS228.004.005.00011 (Box MS228 Shared 3)